Finding Aid for the Carey McWilliams Papers LSC.1319
UCLA Library Special Collections
- 6. Manuscripts, 1896-1981; 18 boxes
  - 6A. Addresses and lectures, 1937-1979; 7.5 boxes
    - [Jack Tenney], undated; 1 item. (Box 66, Folder 10)
    - [Journals of ideas], undated; 3 items. (Box 66, Folder 11)
    - Khrushchev's Visit: Good or Bad?, 1959; 2 items. (Box 66, Folder 12)
      Typewritten manuscript of the opening statement in a debate at Morristown, N.J. with William Rusher.
    - Labor and civil liberties, ca. 1956; 1 item. (Box 66, Folder 13)
    - Labor and the development of the West, 1948 December 31; 2 items. (Box 66, Folder 14)
      Typewritten manuscript of an address delivered at the 23rd conference of the Pacific Coast Economic Association. Includes program.
    - A liberal's plea for conservatism (1 of 3), 1961-1962; 15 items. (Box 66, Folder 15)
      Typewritten outlines of an address delivered at various locations.
    - A liberal's plea for conservatism (2 of 3), 1966-1967; 10 items. (Box 66, Folder 16)
      Typewritten outlines of an address delivered at various locations, and numerous clippings.
    - A liberal's plea for conservatism (3 of 3), 1963-1972; ca. 60 items. (Box 66, Folder 17)
      Typewritten outlines, lecture drafts, and notes, including an essay on Henry S. Kariel. Includes letters, clippings on American politics, and articles.
    - Liberalism today, 1973 January 15; 1 item. (Box 66, Folder 18)
    - The liberals in a period of war crisis, 1941 May 6; 2 items. (Box 66, Folder 19)
      Typewritten manuscripts for an address delivered before the "Social Work Today" luncheon at Long Beach, CA.
    - Liberty in the Warfare State, 1961 December 15; 1 item. (Box 67, Folder 1)
      Typewritten manuscript of an address delivered at the Hotel Commodore.
    - A look at national politics, 1979 November-December; 2 items. (Box 67, Folder 2)
      Typewritten outline for an address delivered at UCLA, and a later version.
    - Make way for tomorrow, 1960 January 10; 2 items. (Box 67, Folder 3)
    - Mass media and race, 1969 April 11; 2 items. (Box 67, Folder 4)
      Typewritten outline for an address in Atlanta, GA.
    - The matter of oaths, undated; 3 items. (Box 67, Folder 5)
      Typewritten outlines and lecture notes.
    - [The McCarran Act], ca. 1952; 2 items. (Box 67, Folder 6)
      Typewritten manuscript of an address sponsored by the Arts, Sciences, and Professions Council, Southern California Chapter, for a meeting against the McCarran Act. Includes event flier.
    - The meaning of the '68 election, ca. 1968; 2 items. (Box 67, Folder 7)
    - Migrants and migratory labor in California, undated; 1 item. (Box 67, Folder 8)
      Typewritten manuscript of an address before the Washington State Conference of Social Workers, April 24.
    - Migrants and the rural poor, 1940, 1977; 23 items. (Box 67, Folder 9)
      Typewritten manuscript of an address given at The Rural Poor Unseen by Policy Makers Conference on March 24-25, 1977 in Phoenix, Arizona. Also contains related correspondence, a program, 2 papers (including one by McWilliams: "Migration and resettlement of the people"), typewritten outlines, and clippings.
    - Minorities and the press, 1973 February 26; 1 item. (Box 67, Folder 10)
    - [Monopolies in the North and East and regional development], undated; 1 item. (Box 67, Folder 11)
    - The Nation's editorials, 1971 March 25; 9 items. (Box 67, Folder 12)
      Typewritten copies of an outline for an address delivered at the University of Illinois. Includes correspondence and a schedule for the lecture series.
    - The Nation's problem, undated; 1 item. (Box 67, Folder 13)
    - The National Citizens Political Action Committee: what it stands for, how it functions, what it means, 1946 April 9; 8 items. (Box 67, Folder 14)
      Copies of an address given at dinner in honor of Henry A. Wallace in Beverly Hills, CA.
    - National defense and human values, undated; 1 item. (Box 67, Folder 15)
    - The need for dissent, 1961-1968; 25 items. (Box 67, Folder 16)
      Assorted lecture outlines and drafts.
    - The need for dissent in American society, 1960-1967; 15 items. (Box 67, Folder 17)
      Assorted lecture drafts and outlines.
    - The new constituencies, 1967 February 25; 2 items. (Box 67, Folder 18)
      Typewritten manuscript and outline of an address given at The Nation's conference on American foreign policy. (See also box 88, folder 1)
    - New forms of political action, 1977 March 14; 1 item. (Box 67, Folder 19)
      Typewritten outline of an address delivered at Cooper Union.
    - The new McCarthyism, ca. 1954-1961; 7 items. (Box 67, Folder 20)
      Assorted lecture outlines and drafts, including a fragment entitled, "The McCarthy era."
    - The new politics, 1968; 3 items. (Box 67, Folder 21)
    - News management, 1970-1971; 6 items. (Box 67, Folder 22)
      Assorted typewritten lecture drafts to be read at various locations.
    - News management: a threat to a free press, 1966-1967; 5 items. (Box 67, Folder 23)
    - News management: threat to democracy, 1968 March 11; 1 item. (Box 67, Folder 24)
    - The 1956 election, undated; 1 item. (Box 68, Folder 1)
    - The 1964 election, ca. 1963-1964; 40 items. (Box 68, Folder 2)
      Typewritten outlines and notes, press releases, and clippings.
    - The 1966 election, 1966 November; 1 item. (Box 68, Folder 3)
      Typewritten manuscript of commentary for CBS Television, and a letter.
    - The 1974 election, 1974 November 3; 1 item. (Box 68, Folder 4)
    - [Notes on UCLA course procedures], 1978-1979; 7 items. (Box 68, Folder 5)
      Typewritten notes serving as the introduction to, and procedural explanation for, a course McWilliams's taught at UCLA. Contains reference to his teaching philosophy and attitudes towards formal education. Includes letters from Robert Towne, David Brodsly, and Lou Cannon.
    - November election: issues and prospects, ca. 1960; 1 item. (Box 68, Folder 6)
    - On understanding America, undated; 1 item. (Box 68, Folder 7)
      Graduation speech lecture notes and manuscript, typewritten.
    - Our freedom is our security, undated; 3 items. (Box 68, Folder 8)
      Typewritten manuscript of an address, and notes.
    - Outlook on civil liberties, 1953 October 31; 2 items. (Box 68, Folder 9)
      Typewritten manuscripts of an address delivered before the United Packinghouse Workers of America's Anti-Discrimination Conference, Chicago, IL. Also entitled, "Outlook on civil rights."
    - Organized racism: a threat to democracy, undated; 1 item. (Box 68, Folder 10)
    - The paradox of racism, undated; 1 item. (Box 68, Folder 11)
    - Perspective on race relations, 1967-1968; 6 items. (Box 68, Folder 12)
      Typewritten outlines and manuscripts, to be read at various locations.
    - Perspective '77, 1977 September 10; 1 item. (Box 68, Folder 13)
    - Political trials, 1971-1975; 14 items. (Box 68, Folder 14)
      Typewritten outline, one letter, and assorted notes, articles, and clippings.
    - [Politics lecture notes], ca. 1950-1959; 10 items. (Box 68, Folder 15)
      Assorted untitled manuscript fragments, notes, outlines, and clipping on various aspects of American politics.
    - Politics: 1976, ca. 1976; 7 items. (Box 68, Folder 16)
      Typewritten outlines and notes.
    - The politics of drift, undated; 2 items. (Box 68, Folder 17)
    - The politics of the 1960s, 1960-1961; 7 items. (Box 68, Folder 18)
      Typewritten outlines and manuscripts, to be read at various locations. Includes outlines entitled, "The issues in 1960."
    - A practical approach to America's race problem, 1961 July 12; 4 items. (Box 68, Folder 19)
    - [The present state of the The Education of Carey McWilliams], 1963 March 27; 3 items. (Box 68, Folder 20)
    - The presidency, 1968 November 5; 5 items. (Box 68, Folder 21)
      Typewritten lecture outline and notes.
    - [The presidency and constitutional freedoms], 1976; 7 items. (Box 68, Folder 22)
      Typewritten lecture outline, leaflets, clippings, and a copy of The Civil Liberties Review.
    - The prevalence of witches, undated; 2 items. (Box 68, Folder 23)
      Typewritten lecture outlines, to be delivered at an undetermined location.
    - The prospects for disarmament, 1963; 5 items. (Box 70, Folder 1)
    - [Race relations], 1945-1949, 1964; 20 items. (Box 70, Folder 2)
      Untitled fragments of lecture drafts, notes, and clippings.
    - Race relations in a post-war world, undated; 1 item. (Box 70, Folder 3)
    - Race relations in the USA, undated; 2 items. (Box 70, Folder 4)
      Incomplete typewritten outline.
    - Race relations: the new myths, 1967 February 23; 3 items. (Box 70, Folder 5)
    - The radical Right, 1962-1963; 3 items. (Box 70, Folder 6)
      Typewritten outline for an address given at N.Y. State College and in Hamden, CT.
    - The rape of Owens Valley, 1978 July; 2 items. (Box 70, Folder 7)
      Photocopy of a typewritten outline for an address in Sun Valley.
    - Reflections on the Hiss case, 1978 May 26; 1 item. (Box 70, Folder 8)
    - Remembering Louise Berman, 1977 November 14; 1 item. (Box 70, Folder 9)
      Typewritten manuscript of an address.
    - Remembering the 1930s, 1975 May 7; 1 item. (Box 70, Folder 10)
      Typewritten manuscript of an address delivered at Yale University.
    - The role of the journal of critical opinion in American journalism, 1956 November 9; 4 items. (Box 70, Folder 11)
      Typewritten manuscript of an address delivered before the Associated Collegiate Press Conference in Cleveland, OH.
    - Role of the media, 1970 October 19; 1 item. (Box 70, Folder 12)
    - Scorecard on the American press, 1936 April 28; 1 item. (Box 70, Folder 13)
      Typewritten outline for an address given in New York.
    - Scorecard on the [American] press, 1961-1967; 13 items. (Box 70, Folder 14)
      Assorted typewritten lecture outlines and drafts, to be read at various locations.
    - A sensible foreign policy, 1962 October 22; 3 items. (Box 70, Folder 15)
    - Six points about H.L. Mencken, undated; 1 item. (Box 70, Folder 16)
      Photocopy of a typewritten outline.
    - [Social ethics], 1969 March 8; 2 items. (Box 70, Folder 17)
      Typewritten outline for an address given at the Cambridge Institute in Boston, MA.
    - Some thoughts on the Bicentennial, 1976 May 1; 6 items. (Box 70, Folder 18)
      Typewritten outlines and notes for an address given at San Diego State.
    - Sore Spots in the American Democracy, 1956 October 19; 3 items. (Box 70, Folder 19)
      Typewritten manuscript of an address delivered in St. Louis before the Missouri Association for Social Welfare. Includes the Association's conference program.
    - The Spanish-speaking: a special case, 1978 December 13; 1 item. (Box 70, Folder 20)
      Typewritten outline of an address given at California State Sacramento.
    - Starr King and the problem of leadership, 1950 October 15; 3 items. (Box 70, Folder 21)
      Typewritten copies of an address delivered before the First Unitarian Church of Los Angeles.
    - Student protest movements, 1967-1969; 14 items. (Box 70, Folder 22)
      Lecture outlines and notes for addresses given at various locations, including Bethany College in Bethany, West Virginia on November 16, 1967. Also contains related letters, 1 black and white photograph, a press release, and newspaper clippings.
    - The student revolt, 1966 March 28; 2 items. (Box 70, Folder 23)
    - [Thanks], undated; 2 items. (Box 70, Folder 24)
      Typewritten outline of a thank-you speech pertaining to The Nation.
    - That awesome space, 1978 July; 1 item. (Box 70, Folder 25)
      Photocopied outline of an address for the Sun Valley Center for Arts and Humanities' Conference "The Writer and the West"
    - Thoughts on the Bicentennial, 1975; 2 items. (Box 70, Folder 26)
      Typewritten outline of an address given in Atlantic City, New Jersey, and a clipping of the published article that appeared in The Nation.
    - Time for a new politics, 1962 November 4; 5 items. (Box 70, Folder 27)
    - Time to think, 1940 April 6; 1 item. (Box 70, Folder 28)
      Copy of an address delivered at the Peace Conference, Knight of Columbus Hall, in San Francisco, CA.
    - To defend these freedoms: by suppression or liberty, undated; 1 item. (Box 70, Folder 29)
      Typewritten lecture.
    - The two-party system, 1966; 9 items. (Box 70, Folder 30)
      Typewritten outlines. Includes a fragment entitled, "Ghouls, ghosts, and the GOP."
    - [University of Southern California Distinguished Achievement Award in Journalism], 1976; 12 items. (Box 71, Folder 1)
      Typewritten outline of McWilliams's acceptance speech. Also includes related letters, the awards' program, and a clipping.
    - Utah's ecclesiastical politics, 1945 December 12; 1 item. (Box 71, Folder 2)
      Typewritten manuscript of an address delivered in Salt Lake City, UT.
    - The vile decade, 1960 June 24; 5 items. (Box 71, Folder 3)
      Typewritten lecture outlines and the draft of a paper presented for the ACLU in San Francisco.
    - Voice of America, ca. 1939-1945; 1 item. (Box 71, Folder 4)
    - The warfare state, 1960-1963; 14 items. (Box 71, Folder 5)
      Typewritten outline, notes, clippings, and articles.
    - What is liberalism?, undated; 4 items. (Box 71, Folder 6)
    - What price civilization?, 1967 October 16; 4 items. (Box 71, Folder 7)
      Assorted typewritten drafts for an address delivered at Cooper Union.
    - What's wrong with our politics, 1966-1968, 1975-1976; 17 items. (Box 71, Folder 8)
      Typewritten outline and notes for an address delivered at the Merced College Talk, and earlier drafts. Includes letters and a brochure from the event.
    - Where are the liberals, ca. 1954; 3 items. (Box 71, Folder 9)
    - Why a labor movement?, 1937 June; 1 item. (Box 71, Folder 10)
      Typewritten manuscript of an address delivered at the University Club.
    - Why dissent in American society?, 1962 May 8; 1 item. (Box 71, Folder 11)
    - Witchhunting and the struggle for power, undated; 1 item. (Box 71, Folder 12)
    - Writers and the war, undated; 1 item. (Box 71, Folder 13)
    - Year of the snake, ca. 1953; 1 item. (Box 71, Folder 14)
      Typewritten manuscript, heavily annotated, on McCarthyism.
  - 6B. Articles and essays, 1927 -1981; 5 boxes
    This subseries contains manuscript drafts and outlines of articles and essays by McWilliams, along with assorted supporting materials. The manuscripts include editorials, memoranda, letters to the editor, forewords to books, a "Dossier" (which summarizes his education, professional activities, and political attitudes), and an annotated copy of his last article, "Los Angeles: a very special city." Arranged alphabetically by title.
    - [Alger Hiss], undated; 4 items. (Box 71, Folder 15)
      Three typewritten manuscripts on Alger Hiss, entitled "The Hiss case controversy" and "That mysterious Woodcock typewriter."
    - The American burden, 1961-1962; 5 items. (Box 71, Folder 16)
      Typewritten manuscript, copy of the published version, and related letters.
    - The American of the Far West, undated; 2 items. (Box 71, Folder 17)
      Typewritten manuscript.
    - The American political vacuum, undated; 1 item. (Box 71, Folder 18)
    - American Tolstoyans, undated; 3 items. (Box 71, Folder 19)
      Typewritten manuscripts.
    - American writing and the social sciences, undated; 1 item. (Box 71, Folder 20)
      Typewritten manuscript, with annotations.
    - Application of Carey McWilliams, ca. 1940; 1 item. (Box 71, Folder 21)
      Typewritten manuscript of a statement for a fellowship (Guggenheim?) to study agricultural labor in Hawaii.
    - [Arthur Samish], 1971; 3 items. (Box 71, Folder 22)
      Typewritten manuscript of a quotation from a McWilliams's article to be used in the book The Secret Boss of California by Samish and Bob Thomas. Also includes related letters.
    - Aspects of national defense, undated; 3 items. (Box 71, Folder 23)
    - Aspects of post-war planning, 1942 October; 1 item. (Box 71, Folder 24)
    - The big fix, undated; 1 item. (Box 71, Folder 25)
      Typewritten manuscript about a scandal in the Los Angeles Police Department and Mickey Cohen, occurring sometime during Mayor Fletch Bowron's fourth term in office.
    - [Bilingual education], 1979 January 11; 1 item. (Box 71, Folder 26)
    - Blue versus gray, undated; 1 item. (Box 71, Folder 27)
    - [The Bridges case], undated; 1 item. (Box 71, Folder 28)
      Typewritten manuscript, heavily annotated.
    - The British presence, 1972, 1978; 7 items. (Box 71, Folder 29)
      Typewritten manuscript, letter, typed notes, and clippings.
    - Bronowski: man of many gifts, ca. 1958-1974; 4 items. (Box 74, Folder 1)
      Typewritten manuscripts, including an untitled piece of Jacob Bronowski, and a memorandum about a series on trends in modern thought.
    - But who's to fix the little house?, 1936 July 13; 1 item. (Box 74, Folder 2)
      Typewritten manuscript for Pacific Weekly.
    - California and the Japanese, 1942 February 10; 1 item. (Box 74, Folder 3)
      Typewritten manuscript on the status of Japanese Americans following Pearl Harbor.
    - The California derby, ca. 1946; 1 item. (Box 74, Folder 4)
      Typewritten manuscript on the senatorial race of Will Rogers, Jr. and California politics.
    - The California explosion, 1976; 2 items. (Box 74, Folder 5)
      Typewritten manuscript on the upsurge of population in California, written for the publication Westways. Also includes a related letter from Frances Ring.
    - [Central Intelligence Agency], ca. 1977; 1 item. (Box 74, Folder 6)
    - Citizen response to the disarmament controversy in America, 1962 November 24; 3 items. (Box 74, Folder 7)
      Typewritten manuscript of a paper prepared for The National Council for Social Studies, Philadelphia, PA.
    - Civil rights: civil liberties, undated; 3 items. (Box 74, Folder 8)
      Typewritten outline and notes regarding calling a meeting on the decline of civil liberties.
    - A climate for ideas, 1973; 4 items. (Box 74, Folder 9)
      Typewritten manuscript regarding The Cooper Union Forum, a clipping of the published article, a related letter, and a brochure.
    - Co-existence has a chance, undated; 1 item. (Box 74, Folder 10)
      Typewritten outline on the Cold War.
    - Communism in America: fact and fantasy, undated; 1 item. (Box 74, Folder 11)
    - Confidential: talk with Stevenson, ca. 1952; 14 items. (Box 74, Folder 12)
      Copies of a typewritten manuscript regarding an off-the-record conversation between McWilliams and Adlai E. Stevenson. Includes a copy of The Nation.
    - [The conflict over racial segregation in the schools], 1956; 2 items. (Box 74, Folder 13)
    - Constitution-conscious, 1935; 2 items. (Box 74, Folder 14)
      Typewritten manuscript, and a clipping of the published article in Pacific Weekly.
    - The counter culture, ca. 1975; 1 item. (Box 74, Folder 15)
      Typewritten manuscript describing a possible book proposal.
    - Culture and society in Southern California, undated; 1 item. (Box 74, Folder 16)
    - Depression post-mortem, ca. 1935; 3 items. (Box 74, Folder 17)
      Typewritten manuscripts and clipping.
    - The dilemma of liberalism, undated; 1 item. (Box 74, Folder 18)
    - [Disaffection with President Carter], 1979 January 11; 1 item. (Box 74, Folder 19)
    - Discovering California, 1975; 3 items. (Box 74, Folder 20)
      Typewritten manuscript, a related letter, and a clipping.
    - Don't blame Orange County, 1973; 3 items. (Box 74, Folder 21)
      Typewritten manuscript; handwritten annotation across top reads, "N.Y. Times, 1973." Related letter from Stanley Mosk.
    - Dossier, ca. 1950; 2 items. (Box 74, Folder 22)
      Typewritten summaries of McWilliams's education, professional activities, and political attitudes, in a full outline format. These refute communist accusations (red-baiting) against him.
    - Dual citizenship, 1942 October 31; 1 item. (Box 74, Folder 23)
      Typewritten manuscript on the citizenship status of Japanese-Americans.
    - Editor The Times, undated; 1 item. (Box 74, Folder 24)
      Typewritten manuscript of a letter to the editor in which McWilliams discusses the Equal Rights Amendment.
    - Editorial memo, 1956 September 3; 1 item. (Box 74, Folder 25)
      Typewritten manuscript on the idea of a "new epoch."
    - The education of Earl Warren, 1974; 4 items. (Box 74, Folder 26)
      Typewritten manuscript, and published version.
    - The emergence of the Hispanic minority, ca. 1979; 2 items. (Box 74, Folder 27)
      Typewritten manuscript and outline.
    - Employment problems of the Spanish-speaking groups, undated; 1 item. (Box 74, Folder 28)
    - The enemy in Pasadena, undated; 1 item. (Box 74, Folder 29)
      Typewritten manuscript on threats against public education.
    - [The environment], undated; 1 item. (Box 74, Folder 30)
      Untitled essay outline on the environment.
    - Ethics in an affluent society, 1966; 21 items. (Box 74, Folder 31)
      Typewritten outlines, drafts, and fragments. Clipping of published version.
    - Evacuation has begun, undated; 1 item. (Box 74, Folder 32)
      Typewritten manuscript on the Tolan Committee and the status of Japanese-Americans.
    - The family farm today, ca. 1955; 1 item. (Box 74, Folder 33)
    - The Fascist follies, undated; 1 item. (Box 74, Folder 34)
    - The figurehead presidency, undated; 1 item. (Box 74, Folder 35)
      Photocopy of a typewritten manuscript on Ronald Reagan.
    - The folklore of earthquakes, 1933 June; 1 item. (Box 74, Folder 36)
      Typewritten manuscript for The American Mercury.
    - [Foreword to From Indians to Chicanos, by Diego Vigil], 1980; 2 items. (Box 74, Folder 37)
      Typewritten manuscript and a related letter.
    - [Foreword to The History of the University of Southern California], 1968-1969; 12 items. (Box 74, Folder 38)
      Typewritten manuscript, and related correspondence.
    - [Foreword to The Jubilant Pilgrim, by Reuben W. Borough], 1964; 5 items. (Box 74, Folder 39)
      Typewritten foreword draft and related correspondence.
    - [Foreword to Saturday's Child, by Ronald Taylor], 1972; 2 items. (Box 77, Folder 1)
    - [Foreword to Spiders in the House, by Ernesto Galarza], 1969; 7 items. (Box 77, Folder 2)
    - The forgotten Mexican, 1951; 2 items. (Box 77, Folder 3)
      Typewritten manuscript, a condensation of a chapter from Brothers Under the Skin, for publication in the Journal of Negro Education Yearbook.
    - Front-page jurists, undated; 2 items. (Box 77, Folder 4)
      Typewritten manuscripts on Los Angeles judges.
    - Furniture: the great Southern California mystery, 1951, 1981; 5 items. (Box 77, Folder 5)
      Typewritten manuscripts and related letters, including one from Frances Ring.
    - [George Sanchez], undated; 1 item. (Box 77, Folder 6)
      Photocopy of a typewritten manuscript honoring George Sanchez.
    - Gilt edge stuff, or, Upset to Fairyland, undated; 2 items. (Box 77, Folder 7)
    - The Gold Rush decade, undated; 1 item. (Box 77, Folder 8)
    - Good neighbors--good friends, 1959; 3 items. (Box 77, Folder 9)
      Typewritten version of a paper presented at a conference, and a related letter.
    - The great exception, undated; 1 item. (Box 77, Folder 10)
    - Growing up in Steamboat, undated; 6 items. (Box 77, Folder 11)
      Typewritten outline, notes, and a clipping.
    - The growth of fear in America, undated; 1 item. (Box 77, Folder 12)
      Typewritten outline. Includes sentence about the UCLA loyalty oath.
    - H. H. Wilson, 1977; 4 items. (Box 77, Folder 13)
      Photocopy of a typewritten manuscript, and clippings.